CURRICULUM VITAE

Jeffrey Hanson

School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Queensland, Australia 4306

☑ jeffrey.hanson@uqconnect.edu.au

jeffrey-hanson.com

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research concerns the challenges involved in conserving biodiversity. I am interested in understanding how areas can be managed to achieve conservation objectives for minimal cost. In particular, I specialize in operationalizing ecological and evolutionary processes to develop plans for protected area systems that maximize the long-term persistence of biodiversity.

EDUCATION

- 2013–2018 PhD, Biology, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Richard Fuller and Jonathon Rhodes, thesis: Conserving evolutionary processes.)
- 2011–2012 BS (Hons), First Class, The University of Queensland, Australia (Advisors: Steve Salisbury, Craig Franklin, Hamish Campbell, and Ross Dwyer, thesis: *Using stable isotopes to assess the relationship between body-size, habitat use and diet in estuarine crocodiles (Crocodylus porosus)*)
- 2007–2010 BS, Major in Ecology, The University of Queensland, Australia

PROFESSIONAL POSITIONS

- 2012–2013 Research Assistant to Richard Fuller, The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2012–2013 Research Assistant to Jonathon Rhodes, The University of Queensland, Australia
- 2012 Casual Professional Staff, The School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland, Australia

EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES

Classroom Instruction, The University of Queensland, Australia

2013–2015 Professional tutor to the "Field Ecology" course, coordinated by Myron Zalucki

Workshop Instruction

- 2017 Use of Machine Learning in Conservation, Moving beyond just Maxent and SDMs coordinated by Falk Huettmann at the 28th International Congress for Conservation Biology (ICCB).
- 2015 Geospatial Analysis in R coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer, Rebbecca Runting and Jutta Beher at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.

Smoothing the Marxan Flow with R coordinated by Matthew Watts at the Student Conference of Conservation Science, Australia.

- 2013 Introduction to Geospatial Analysis coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.
 - Introduction to Spatial Data Analysis in R workshop coordinated by Hawthorne Beyer at The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2011 Introducing R coordinated by Simon Blomberg at The University of Queensland, Australia.

PUBLICATIONS

Journal articles

- 2018 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP & Fuller RA raptr: Representative and Adequate Prioritization Toolkit in R. *Methods in Ecology & Evolution*, 9: 320–330.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Riginos C & Fuller RA (2017) Environmental and geographic variables are effective surrogates for genetic variation in conservation planning. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 114: 12755–12760.

Mather AT, **Hanson JO**, Pope LC & Riginos C (2017) Comparative phylogeography of two co-distributed but ecologically distinct rainbowfishes of far-northern Australia. *Journal of Biogeography*, 45: 127–141.

Dhanjal-Adams KL, **Hanson JO**, Murray NJ, Phinn SR, Wingate VR, Mustin K, Lee JR, Allan JR, Cappadonna JL, Studds CE, Clemens RS, Roelfsema CM & Fuller RA (2016) Distribution and protection of intertidal habitats in Australia. *Emu* **116**: 208–214.

Dudaniec RY, Worthington Wilmer J, **Hanson JO**, Warren M, Bell S & Rhodes JR (2016) Dealing with uncertainty in landscape genetic resistance models: a case of three co-occurring marsupials. *Molecular Ecology*, **25**: 470–486.

Auerbach NA, Wilson KA, Tulloch AI, Rhodes JR, **Hanson JO** & Possingham HP (2015) Effects of threat management interactions on conservation priorities. Conservation Biology, **29**: 1626–1635.

Bunton JD, Ernst AT, **Hanson JO**, Beyer HL, Hammill E, Runge CA, Venter O, Possingham HP & Rhodes JR (2015) Integrated planning of linear infrastructure and conservation offsets. In Weber, T, McPhee, MJ & Andersson RS (eds) *MODSIM* 2015, 21st International Congress on Modelling and Simulation. Modelling and Simulation Society of Australia and New Zealand, December 2015, pp. 1427–1433.

Hanson JO, Salisbury SW, Campbell HA, Dwyer RG, Jardine TD & Franklin CE (2015) Feeding across the food web: The interaction between diet, movement and body size in estuarine crocodiles (*Crocodylus porosus*). *Austral Ecology*, **40**: 275–286.

Rabeb D, Othman DS, Essilfie AT, Hansbro PM, **Hanson JO**, McEwan AG & Kappler U (2015) Maturation of molybdoenzymes and its influence on the pathogenesis of non-typeable *Haemophilus* influenzae. *Frontiers in Microbiology*, **6**: 01219.

Runge CA, Watson JEM, Butchart HM, **Hanson JO**, Possingham HP & Fuller RA (2015) Protected areas and global conservation of migratory birds. *Science*, **350**: 1255–1258.

Popular science articles

2015 Beher J & **Hanson JO** (2015) Welcome to the Mapotron. *Decision Point*, **86**: 10–11.

PEER REVIEW ACTIVITIES

I have reviewed submissions to following journals: Austral Ecology, Conservation Letters, Diversity and Distributions, Global Change Biology, and PLoS ONE.

PRESENTATIONS

Conference presentations

- Hanson JO, Schuster R, Morrell N, Strimas-Mackey M, Watts ME, Arcese P, Bennett JR, Possingham HP. (2018) prioritizr: Systematic conservation prioritization in R. Oral presentation to UseR! 2018, Brisbane, Australia.
- 2016 **Hanson JO**, Rhodes JR, Possingham HP, Fuller RA (2016) RAPR: Representative and Adequate Prioritizations in R. Oral presentation to Society for Conservation Biology 4th Oceania Congress, Brisbane, Australia.
- Hanson JO, Rhodes JR, Fuller RA (2014) Conservation planning for intra-specific biodiversity using surrogates. Oral presentation to the Meeting of the Minds miniconference at The University of Queensland, Brisbane, Australia.

Seminars

- 2017 Systematic conservation prioritization in R presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.
- 2016 Biodiversity processes in reserve-selection presented to members of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation Science at The University of Queensland, Australia.

Scientific meetings and networking events

- 2018 rOpenSci Unconference, Melbourne, Australia.
- 2017 R Unconference hosted by the Brisbane Users of R Group, Brisbane, Australia.
- 2016 rOpenSci Unconference, Brisbane, Australia.